Society for the Preservation of Water Resources; Records apap061
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Wilmorite Project, 1918-1995; 4; 5.43 cubic ft.
  - Wilmorite, Schenectady Aquifer, Wilmorite and the Army Corps of Engineers, 1983-1984 (Box 9A (4-Wilmorite Project), Folder 2)
  - Wilmorite, Schenectady Aquifer, Wilmorite and the Army Corps of Engineers, 1985-1988; 1994-1995; Undated (Box 9A (4-Wilmorite Project), Folder 3)
  - Correspondence on Wilmorite, 1985 April-1985 May (Box 10 (4-Wilmorite Project), Folder 1)
  - Correspondence on Wilmorite, 1985 June-1985 July (Box 10 (4-Wilmorite Project), Folder 2)
  - Correspondence on Wilmorite, 1985 August-1985 October (Box 10 (4-Wilmorite Project), Folder 3)
  - Correspondence on Wilmorite, 1985 November-1986 March (Box 10 (4-Wilmorite Project), Folder 4)
  - Correspondence on Wilmorite, 1986 April-1986 June (Box 10 (4-Wilmorite Project), Folder 5)
  - Correspondence on Wilmorite, 1986 July-1986 December (Box 10 (4-Wilmorite Project), Folder 6)
  - Correspondence on Wilmorite, 1987 January-1987 May (Box 10 (4-Wilmorite Project), Folder 7)
  - Correspondence on Wilmorite, 1987 June-1987 December (Box 10 (4-Wilmorite Project), Folder 8)
  - Correspondence on Wilmorite, 1988 (Box 10 (4-Wilmorite Project), Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 1981-1989 (Box 10 (4-Wilmorite Project), Folder 10)
- Water Supply Applications, 1978-1985; 5; 1.2 cubic ft.
  This series includes records concerning applications to buy land over the Great Flats Aquifer that the city of Schenectady and the town of Rotterdam submitted in order to protect their water supply. Includes correspondence, hearing transcripts, intervention papers, reply briefs, and post-hearing briefs.
  - Appraisal Report, ca. 1985 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 9-10)
  - Correspondence, 1984 September (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1984 September-1984 November (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1984 November (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1984 December-1985 October (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 14)
  - Freedom of Information Requests and Material, Schmid, Marjorie, 1985 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 15)
  - Hearings, Cobblestone Church Case, 1985 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 16)
  - Hearings, Groundwater Management Program, and Summary, 1984 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 17)
  - Hearings, Intervention by City of Schenectady, 1984 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 18)
  - Hearings, Intervention by the Department of Environmental Conservation, 1984 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 19)
  - Hearings, Intervention of International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftsmen, 1985 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 20)
  - Hearings, Intervention by Mantica, Paul F., 1985 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 21)
  - Hearings, Intervention, Miscellaneous Material, 1985 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 22)
  - Hearings, Intervention by Rustay, Robert C., 1982-1985 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 23)
  - Hearings, Intervention by Society for the Preservation of the Aquifer, 1984-1985 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 24)
  - Hearings, Intervention by Town of Rotterdam, Appraisal Report, 1985 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 25)
  - Hearings, Intervention by Town of Rotterdam, Correspondence and Notes, 1978; 1981-1984 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 26)
  - Hearings, Intervention by Town of Rotterdam, 1984-1985 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 27)
  - Hearings, Intervention by Town of Rotterdam, 1982; 1985 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 28)
  - Hearings, Intervention by Town of Rotterdam, 1984 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 29)
  - Hearings, Intervention by Wilmorite, 1985 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 30)
  - Hearings, Kagay's Notes, 1985 (Box 4 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 31-32)
  - Hearings, Real Estate Appraisals, 1985 (Box 5 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 1)
  - Hearings, Reply Brief of City of Schenectady and Town of Niskayuna, 1985 (Box 5 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 2)
  - Hearings, Reply Brief of Reformed Church Intervenors, 1985 (Box 5 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 3)
  - Hearings, Reply Brief of Rustay, Robert C., 1985 (Box 5 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 4)
  - Hearings, Reply Brief of Schmid, Marjorie L., 1985 (Box 5 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 5)
  - Hearings, Reply Brief of the Society for the Preservation of Water Resources, 1985 (Box 5 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 6)
  - Hearings, Reply Brief of Town of Rotterdam, 1985 (Box 5 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 7)
  - Hearings, Reply Brief of Wilmorite, 1985 (Box 5 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 8)
  - Hearings, Schedule for Briefs, and MacArthur's Opening Statement, 1985 (Box 5 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 9)
  - Hearings, Transcripts of Testimony of Putman, George W., Undated (Box 5 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 10)
  - Post-Hearing Briefs, 1985 (Box 5 (5-Water Supply Applications), Folder 11-14)
- Bonded Concrete Project, 1960-1961; 1972; 1974; 1979; 1982-1994; 6; 1.65 cubic ft.
  This series includes records concerning SPWR's project to prevent Bonded Concrete from mining gravel in the Great Flats Aquifer. Includes draft environmental impact statements (DEIS), hearing transcripts, correspondence, application responses, and related material.
  - Correspondence, Preliminary, 1982 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 15)
  - Decisions by Department of Environmental Conservation, 1984 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 16)
  - Draft Environmental Impact Statement, 1982 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 17)
  - Draft Environmental Impact Statement, Supplement, 1982 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 18)
  - Draft Environmental Impact Statement, Supplement III, Mining and Reclamation Plan, 1985 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 19)
  - Draft Environmental Impact Statement, Correspondence and Comments, 1982 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 20)
  - Draft Environmental Impact Statement, Correspondence and Comments, 1983 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 21)
  - Hearings, Correspondence Concerning, 1983 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 22)
  - Hearings, Exhibits, 1960-1961; 1972; 1974; 1979; 1982 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 23)
  - Hearings, Notes by Kagay, 1983 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 24)
  - Hearings, Rebuttal Testimony, Clemente, Andrew E., 1983 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 25)
  - Hearings, Rebuttal Testimony, Clemente, Salvatore, 1983 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 26)
  - Hearings, Rebuttal Testimony, Clesceri, Nicholas L., 1983 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 27)
  - Hearings, Rebuttal Testimony, DeLuke, Lewis A., 1983 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 28)
  - Hearings, Rebuttal Testimony, Dunn, James R., 1983 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 29)
  - Hearings, Rebuttal Testimony, George, Carl J., 1983 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 30)
  - Hearings, Rebuttal Testimony, Hewitt, Philip C., 1983 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 31)
  - Hearings, Rebuttal Testimony, Hubbard, John E., 1983 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 32)
  - Hearings, Technical Reports for Higgins, Roberts, Beyerl & Coan, 1983 (Box 5 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 33-34)
  - Hearings, Transcripts, 1983 (Box 6 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 1-4)
  - Hearings, Transcripts and Revised Ruling, 1983 (Box 6 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 5)
  - Maps, Property of Bonded Concrete and the Aquifer, 1984 (Box 6 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 6)
  - Mining Permit, Correspondence Concerning, 1983-1984 (Box 6 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 7)
  - Track Safety Standards, Federal Railroad Administration, 1982 (Box 6 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 8)
  - Application Information, Appeals, and Interim Decisions, 1990 (Box 11 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 1)
  - Application Responses, 1987 (Box 11 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 2)
  - Application Responses, 1988-1989 (Box 11 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 3)
  - Bonded Concrete Information, 1985; 1987-1988 (Box 11 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 4)
  - Bonded Concrete Information, 1989-1990 (Box 11 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 5)
  - Bonded Concrete Information, 1991 (Box 11 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 6)
  - Bonded Concrete Information, 1992; 1994; Undated (Box 11 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 7)
  - Comments and Environmental Impact Statements, 1986 (Box 11 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Bonded Concrete, 1989 May-1989 December (Box 12 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 1)
  - Direct Examinations, 1982 (Box 12 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 2)
  - Drafts of a Manuscript by John Kagay, 1991 (Box 12 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 3)
  - Exhibits 1-2, 4-6, 8, 10-11, 1987; 1989 (Box 12 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 4)
  - Engineering Reports, 1987 (Box 12 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 5)
  - Federal Register, 1987; 1989 (Box 12 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 6)
  - Permit Material, Public Hearings, and Memorandums, 1985; 1987; 1989 (Box 12 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 7)
  - Position Statements and Presentation, 1989 (Box 12 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 8)
  - Questions, Permit Conditions, and Maps, 1983 (Box 12 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 9)
  - Schenectady Chemicals, Inc., 1991 (Box 12 (6-Bonded Concrete Project), Folder 10)
- Broadway Mall Project, 1968; 1980-1981; 7; 0.2 cubic ft.
  The records in this series concern plans to build Broadway Mall in downtown Schenectady, which was of interest to the Society for the Preservation of Water Resources as a possible alternate site for Wilmorite's Rotterdam Square Mall. Includes draft environmental impact statements (DEIS), environmental assessment forms (EAF), and related material.
  - Draft Environmental Impact Statement, Reference Material, 1968; 1980-1981 (Box 6 (7-Broadway Mall Project), Folder 9-10)
  - Draft Environmental Impact Statement and Related Materials, 1981 (Box 6 (7-Broadway Mall Project), Folder 11)
  - Draft Community Impact Analysis, 1980 (Box 6 (7-Broadway Mall Project), Folder 12)
  - Environmental Assessment Form and Related Material, 1980-1981 (Box 6 (7-Broadway Mall Project), Folder 13)
  - Economic and Market Study of Downtown Schenectady, ca. 1980 (Box 6 (7-Broadway Mall Project), Folder 14)
- News Clippings, 1971-1999; 8; 0.63 cubic ft.
  The news clipping files cover matters of interest to the Society for the Preservation of Water Resources. Included are general files of contemporary news clippings as well as files for older clippings. The news clippings are very strong from the years 1987-1992, and are in chronological order. Most clippings are glued onto binder paper.
  Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
  - Crossgates Mall and General, 1981-1986 (Box 6 (8-News Clippings), Folder 15)
  - General, 1982 June-1983 April (Box 6 (8-News Clippings), Folder 16)
  - General, 1983 April-1983 December (Box 6 (8-News Clippings), Folder 17)
  - General, 1984 January-1984 December (Box 6 (8-News Clippings), Folder 18)
  - General, 1985 January-1986 June (Box 6 (8-News Clippings), Folder 19)
  - General, 1986 July-1986 December (Box 6 (8-News Clippings), Folder 20)
  - Old News Clippings File, 1971; 1977-1982 (Box 6 (8-News Clippings), Folder 21)
  - Wilmorite News Clippings, 1978-1982 (Box 6 (8-News Clippings), Folder 22)
  - News Clippings, Pre-1987, Undated (Box 13 (8-News Clippings), Folder 1)
  - News Clippings, 1987-1988 (Box 14 (8-News Clippings), Folder 1)
  - News Clippings, 1989 (Box 14 (8-News Clippings), Folder 2)
  - News Clippings, 1990-1991 (Box 14 (8-News Clippings), Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1992; 1998; 1999 (Box 14 (8-News Clippings), Folder 4)
- Maps, Photographs, Drawings, 1975; 1978-1982; 9; 2 cubic ft.
  This series includes all large cartographic and pictorial records. Included are some for the Broadway Mall project, Rotterdam Square project, and maps of the city of Schenectady and the town of Rotterdam. There are over forty maps that are included in this series that have not yet been flattened or processed and as a result, the size of this series is not accurate at the present time.
  - Broadway Mall (assumed), Downtown Schenectady, Alternate Site, aerial photograph, ca. 1981 (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
  - Broadway Mall (assumed), Downtown Schenectady, Alternate Site, blueprint of aerial photograph, ca. 1981 (Oversized 1, Folder 2)
  - Broadway Mall, Downtown Site Development, 4 sheets, 18 May 1979 (Oversized 1, Folder 3)
  - Great Flats, Flood Levels, flipcharts (hand drawn charts and maps) by J. Duccan, ca. 1981 (Oversized 1, Folder 4)
  - Great Flats, Flood Storage Volume, manuscript map on graph paper, areas planimetered by John Kagay, ca. 1981 (Oversized 1, Folder 5)
  - Great Flats, Portions of Randall Sheets No. 23, 24, 25, 46, 47, 48, composite topographic map by C.T. Male Associates, P.C., 1978 December (Oversized 1, Folder 6)
  - Rotterdam Square, blueprint maps by Haley and Aldrich, Inc., 1981 June (Oversized 1, Folder 7)
  - a. Groundwater Flow in Delta Sand Deposits (Fig. 8A), Undated
  - b. Thickness of Near-Surfaces Low-Permeability Soil (Fig. 9A), Undated
  - c. Piexometric Contours and Groundwater Flow Pattern (Fig. 7A), Undated
  - d. Site Area and Subsurface Explorations (Fig. 2A), Undated
  - Rotterdam Square, blueprint map by Sear Brown Associates, P.C., Exhibit O, Limit of Flooding Due to the Possible Backwater of the Mohawk River, 3 June 1981 (Oversized 1, Folder 8)
  - Rotterdam Square, blueprint maps by Sear Brown Associates, P. C., 6 February 1981 (Oversized 1, Folder 9)
  - a. Plan Showing Relocation and Widening of Campbell Road, Undated
  - b. Total Area of Wetlands Within Projected Site; Total Area Eliminated by Proposed Construction; Wetlands to Remain, Undated
  - Rotterdam Square, blueprint maps by Sear Brown Associates, P. C., Undated (Oversized 1, Folder 10)
  - a. Exhibit D: Existing Conditions--Development Site, 1981 June 26
  - b. Exhibit E1: Poentic Kill--Existing Conditions Poentic Kill and limits of wetlands), 9 February 1981
  - c. Exhibit E2: Poentic Kill--Existing Conditions Flow and limits of wetlands), 14 June 1981
  - d. Exhibit E3: Poentic Kill--Existing Conditions (Flow), 14 June 1981
  - e. Exhibit E4: Poentic Kill--Existing Conditions (Bridges, roads, walls and ditches along Poentic Kill), 9 February 1981
  - f. Exhibit E5: Poentic Kill--Existing Conditions (Profile of kill), 9 February 1981
  - g. Exhibit E6: Poentic Kill--Location Map, 26 June 1981
  - h. Exhibit E7: Poentic Kill--Centerline Profile, Poentic Kill Dike, Sans Souci Bridge, Southeasterly, 22 June 1981
  - i. Exhibit F: Existing Conditions--Park Parcel, 6 February 1981
  - j. Exhibit G: Rotterdam Square--Grading and Drainage Plan, 6 February 1981
  - k. Exhibit H: Rotterdam Square--Utility Plan, 6 February 1981
  - l. Exhibit I: Rotterdam Square--Creek Relocation and Erosion-- Siltation Control, 6 February 1981
  - m. Exhibit K2: Creek Cross Sections, 26 June 1981
  - n. Exhibit P1: Poenties Kill--Centerline Profile, Campbell Road, Northwesterly, 2000 Feet Along Poenties Kill, Profile No. 3, 22 June 1981
  - o. Exhibit P2: Poenties Kill, Centerline Profile, Campbell Road, Southeasterly Along Northeasterly, Radio Station Property Line, Profile Nos. 1 and 2, 22 June 1981
  - p. Exhibit P3: Poentic Kill Dike, Centerline Profile, Sans Souci Bridge Southeasterly, Profile No. 4, 22 June 1981
  - Rotterdam Square, blueprint sketches by J. Duccan, ca. 1981 (Oversized 1, Folder 11)
  - a. Wilmorite--Problems: Traffic, Flooding, Wetlands, Stream, Salt, Sewage, Aquifer, Undated
  - b. Wilmorite--Area Traffic Flows: Schenectady, Scotia Glenville, Rotterdam, Undated
  - Rotterdam Square--Critical Aquifer Area: Water Lines and Planned Sewer Main, map with overlay transparency of outfall sewer line, prob. by Society for the Preservation of the Aquifer, ca. 1981 (Oversized 1, Folder 12)
  - Rotterdam Square, Great Falls Area and Alternate Proposals for Floodwater Storage Mitigation, map by Sear Brown Associates, P.C., 6 February 1981; 1981 June 26 (Oversized 1, Folder 13)
  - Rotterdam Square, Planting Plan, by Sear Brown Associates, P. C., 24 February 1981 (Oversized 1, Folder 14)
  - Rotterdam Square, Water District Extension Map, Exhibit M, blueprint map by Sear Brown Associates, P.C., 6 February 1981 (Oversized 1, Folder 15)
  - Rotterdam, Town, Sewer District No. 2, Water Treatment Facilities Project, Contract # 1, Outfall Sewer, 28 pages of maps by C.T. Male Associates, P.C., 1980 June (Oversized 1, Folder 16)
  - Schenectady, City, Tax Map by Aero Service for Real Property Tax Service Agency, 19 December 1975 (Oversized 1, Folder 17)
  - Schenectady, Scotia, Rotterdam, blueprint of aerial photograph, ca. 1981 (Oversized 1, Folder 18)
  - Westview Mall, Preliminary Site Plan, map by Sear Brown Associates, P.C., ca. 1981 (Oversized 1, Folder 19)
- Other Projects, 1986-1991; 1994-1995; 10; 0.66 cubic ft.
  Both the projects in this series, the Guildercrest Development and the Schermerhorn Hollow Village were projects in Rotterdam that centered around developing land that would have an impact on Schenectady County's aquifer. The series include correspondence, draft statements, and court material.
  Arranged chronologically by project.
  - Correspondence, Guildercrest Development, 1989-1990 (Box 15 (10-Other Projects), Folder 1)
  - Guildercrest Development, 1986-1991 (Box 15 (10-Other Projects), Folder 2)
  - Guildercrest Development, 1991 (Box 15 (10-Other Projects), Folder 3)
  - Schermerhorn Hollow Village, 1994-1995 (Box 15 (10-Other Projects), Folder 4)